<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of vvithin the dioces of Ely in the first visitation of the R. Reverend Father in God Matthevv, Lord Bishop of Ely.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1638</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Ely. Bishop (1638-1667 : Wren)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R960</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835857</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">84</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68015)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 84)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1350:3, 1413:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of vvithin the dioces of Ely in the first visitation of the R. Reverend Father in God Matthevv, Lord Bishop of Ely.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1638</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Ely. Bishop (1638-1667 : Wren)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Badger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Incorrectly identified as STC 10245 on reel 1350.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Thomason Collection, British Library (Thomason Tracts and Early English books, 1641-1700) and in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.) Library (Early English books, 1475-1640).</note>
                  <note>Appears at (Early English books, 1475-1640) reels 1350 and 1413 (Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.) Library copy) and at (The Thomason Tracts and Early English books, 1641-1700) reels 41 and 265 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wren, Matthew, 1585-1667.</term>
               <term>Church of England. --  Diocese of Ely.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:84:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:84:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES <hi>TO BE</hi> INQVIRED OF VVITHIN THE DIOCES OF <hi>ELY: In the firſt Viſitation of the R. Reverend Father in God,</hi> MATTHEVV, LORD BISHOP OF <hi>ELY.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of phoenix rising out of flames</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Richard Badger.</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:84:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Tenour of the Oath to be miniſtred to the</hi> Church-wardens, and any other of every Pariſh, that ſhall be ſworne to make Preſentments.</head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that you, and every one of you, ſhall and will truly conſider, and diligently enquire of every one of theſe Articles here given you in charge, and of all the branches thereof, and make true anſwer to all particulars therein demanded; and that all affection, or favour, or hatred, or hope of reward or gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure, or malice of any perſon, and all other pretences ſet aſide, you ſhall and will preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch perſon of your Pariſh, or within it, as hath committed any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or fault, or made any default mentioned in any of theſe Articles, or which is vehemently ſuſpected, or otherwiſe defamed of any ſuch offence, fault, or default; wherein you ſhall deale uprightly and fully according to the truth, neither preſenting, nor ſparing to preſent any contrary to the truth: Having in this action God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine truth and vertue, and to ſuppreſſe vice, and to diſcharge your owne conſciences. So help you God, and the Holy Contents of this Booke.</p>
            <closer>GOD SAVE THE KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:84:2"/>
            <head>Articles to be inquired of in the Dioces of <hi>Ely,</hi> at the Viſitation, holden in the yeare of our LORD, 1638.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. Concerning Religion, Doctrine, and Church-government.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>RE there any abiding in your Pariſh, or reſorting to it, who (as farre as you know, or haue credibly heard from perſons of déeper iudgment) do at any time preach, teach, deliuer, publiſh or maintaine any hereſie, or any erroneous &amp; falſe opinion contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of CHRIST, or any ſentence, matter, or cauſe, which hath heretofore béene determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ordered or adiudged to be hereſie, by the authority of the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scriptures, or by the firſt foure generall Councels, or any of them, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generall Councell, determining the ſame to be hereſie by the expreſſe words of holy Scripture? Or are there any which do deny or impugne any of the 39 Articles of Religion agréed vpon in <hi>Anno</hi> 1562. and eſtabliſhed in the Church of England? And is the Declaration, which the Kings Maieſty prefixed before thoſe 39 Articles, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſelling of the queſtions late in difference, duly obſerued by all within your Pariſh, according to His Maieſties commandement?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Be there any in your Pariſh that haue denied, or perſwaded any other to deny, withſtand or impugne the Kings Maieſties authority and ſupremacy, in cauſes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall within this Realme?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Be there any in your Pariſh that haue affirmed, that the Forme of conſecrating Biſhops, and making Prieſts and Deacons, as it is vſed in the Church of England, is not holy, right, true and lawfull? Or that the Gouernment of this Church, vnder the Kings Maieſtie by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Officers, is vnlawfull or antichriſtian?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Is there in your Pariſh any that hath béene, or is vehemently ſuſpected to have béene preſent at any vnlawfull aſſemblies, conuenticles, or méetings, vnder colour or pretence of any exerciſe of Religion? or do any affirme and maintaine ſuch méetings to be lawfull?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Be there any abiding in, or reſorting to your Pariſh, that are commonly repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be ill affected in matter of the religion profeſſed in our Church, or taken to be Recuſant Papiſts, or factious ſeparatiſts, refuſing to repaire vnto the Church to heare diuine Seruice, and to receiue the holy Communion? Or that haue or do pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, ſell or diſperſe, or conueigh to others any ſuperſtitious, ſeditious, or ſchiſmaticall Bookes, Libels, or Writings, touching the Religion, State, or Eccleſiaſticall gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdome of England? Preſent their names, qualities and conditions, if you know or haue heard of any.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Haue any in your Pariſh ſpoken or declared anything in derogation or depraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the forme of Gods worſhip, and the ſet forme of common prayer preſcribed and eſtabliſhed in the Church of England, or in diſlike of the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or of the other Rites and Ceremonies ſet forth and preſcribed in the Book of Common Prayer and the Canons Eccleſiaſticall? Or do any preach, ſpeak, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the Booke of Common Prayer containeth any thing that is repugnant to the holy Scripture, or not meet to be vſed? Or do vſe any ſcomfull words againſt thoſe godly Sermons, called, the Homilies of the Church?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:84:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Concerning Publike Prayer, and the Adminiſtration of the Holy Sacraments, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HAth any in your Pariſh cauſed, procured, or maintained any Miniſter, to ſay any common or publike prayer, or to adminiſter the Sacrament of Baptiſme, or of the Lords Supper, otherwiſe or in any other maner, than is mentioned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer? Or hath any interrupted, hindered, let, or diſturbed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miniſter in reading of diuine Seruice, or adminiſtring the Sacraments in ſuch manner as is mentioned in the ſaid booke? Or hath any interrupted him in his preaching, or reading the Homilies?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Is the Sacrament of Baptiſme rightly and duly adminiſtred according to the forme preſcribed in the Booke of Common Prayer; with due obſeruation of all Rites and Ceremonies preſcribed to be vſed in the ſame, without adding or altering of any part of any prayers, or interrogatories? Is the ſigne of the Croſſe euery time vſed, and the Surplice neuer but worne in the adminiſtring of it?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hath the adminiſtration of the Sacrament of Baptiſme béene at any time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred longer than till the next Sunday or Holiday, immediately following the birth of the childe? And do they all come to Church when a child is to be baptized, at, or about the beginning of diuine Seruice? And is the baptizing performed immediately after the ſecond Leſſon?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Hath the Sacrament of Baptiſme béen refuſed to be adminiſtred to any children borne in, or out of wedlock, their birth being made known to the Miniſter of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and they offered vnto him to be baptized? Or haue any ſuch children died vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Haue the parents of the childe baptiſed, béene at any time admitted to be Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or Godmothers to the ſame? Or haue any béene admitted to be Godfathers or Godmothers to any childe, before they haue receiued the holy Communion? Or haue there béene admitted more (or leſſe) than two Godfathers and one Godmother for a male child, and two Godmothers and one Godfather for a female? Or haue any God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers or Godmothers vſed any other anſwers or ſpéech in Baptiſme, than is by the Book of Common Prayer appointed? Or haue they giuen to the children baptiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny name that is abſurd, or inconuenient for ſo holy an action?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Haue any children béene baptiſed in priuate houſes (except vpon great neceſſity: and if ſo, what was the ſame?) or by any Lay-perſon, or Midwife, or Popiſh Prieſt, or by any other than your owne Miniſter? And haue all children which were priuately baptized, if they liued, béene afterwards brought to your Church, that the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Miniſter of the Pariſh (in caſe they were not baptiſed by him) might be certified, whether they were lawfully baptiſed or no?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Haue the children that haue béene borne to any Popiſh Recuſant in your Pariſh, béene publikely baptiſed in your Pariſh Church, by your owne Parſon, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate? Or by whom elſe were they baptiſed, or where, to your knowledge, or as you haue heard? you are to giue all the notice you can, both of them and of their Parents.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Hath the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper béene duly and reuerently adminiſtred in your Church or Chappell, ſo often, and at ſuch conuenient times, that, at leaſt thrice euery yéere (whereof once at Eaſter) euery Pariſhioner within your Pariſh, being of the age of 16 yéeres, or vpwards, might receiue the ſame?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Hath the ſaid bleſſed Sacrament béen deliuered vnto any, or receiued by any the Communicants within your Pariſh, that did vnrcuerently either ſit, ſtand, or leane; or that did not deuoutly and humbly knéele vpon their knées, in plaine and open view, without colluſion or hypocriſie?</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:84:3"/>10 Haue any of your Pariſh, which are openly knowne to liue in notorious ſinne without repentance; or any excommunicate perſons or ſchiſmaticks, common and notorious deprauers of the Religion and Gouernment of this Realme (without vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained ſorrow ſhewed by them for their impiety and wickedneſſe) béene admitted to be partakers of the holy Communion?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Hath any of your Pariſh béen debarred from the ſaid holy Communion, without iuſt cauſe, or without intimation preſently giuen to the Ordinarie or Biſhop of the Dioces? Name euery ſuch perſon, and the perſon that debarred him, or them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. Concerning the Church, the furniture, and poſſeſſions thereof.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HAue you a Pariſh Church and Chancell now ſtanding, and in vſe, or is the ſame prophaned, or demoliſhed, in part, or in whole?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Haue you in your Church or Chappell, the whole Bible in the largeſt Volume, of the laſt tranſlation, the Booke of Common Prayer, the two Bookes of Homilies, and Biſhop <hi>Iewels</hi> Works, all well and fairely bound? And haue you alſo in your Church, the forme of the Diuine Seruice, for the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of Nouember, and for the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of March, and the Book of Conſtitutions or Canons Eccleſiaſticall?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Haue you in your Church or Chappell, a Font of ſtone ſet and faſtened in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vſuall place, whole and cleane, and fit to hold water? A conuenient and decent Communion Table, with a carpet of ſilke, or ſome other decent ſtuffe, continually laid vpon the Table at the time of diuine Seruice; and a faire linnen cloth thereon laid, at the time of adminiſtring the Communion? what did either of them coſt? what be they now worth in value? And is the ſame Table placed conueniently, ſo as the Miniſter may beſt be heard in his adminiſtration, and the greateſt number may reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently communicate? To that end doth it ordinarily ſtand vp at the Eaſt end of the Chancell where the Altar in former times ſtood, the ends thereof being placed North and South? Is it at any time vſed vnreuerently, by leaning or ſitting on it, throwing hats or any thing elſe vpon it, or writing on it; or is it abuſed to any other prophane or common vſe? Are there any ſteps or aſcents in your Chancell vp to the Communion Table? Haue you alſo a decent raile of wood (or ſome other comely incloſure coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with cloth or ſilk) placed handſomely aboue thoſe ſteps, before the Holy Table, néere one yard high, and reaching croſſe from the North wall to the South (except by the order of the Dioceſan it be made with the ends returning vnto the Eaſt wall) with two conuenient doores to open before the Table: And if it be a Raile, are the Pillars or Balliſters thereof ſo cloſe, that doggs may not any where get in? Alſo are the ten Commandements ſet vp in your Church or Chappell, where the people may ſee and read them; and other choſen ſentences written vpon the wals of your ſaid Church or Chappell, in places conuenient for the ſame purpoſe?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Haue you in your ſaid Church or Chappell a conuenient ſeat for your Miniſter to read diuine Seruice in? Where and in what part of the Church doth it ſtand? how farre from the Chancell? and which way doth the ſtanding thereof cauſe the Miniſter to turne his face, when he knéeleth therein at prayer? Haue you alſo a comely Pulpit ſet vp in a conuenient place, with a decent Cloth or Cuſhion for the ſame? Haue you a comely large Surplice? what coſt it by the yard? and how long haue you had the ſame? Haue you alſo a faire Communion Cup of ſiluer, and a couer agréeable to the ſame; a Flagon of ſiluer or pewter, with all other things and Ornaments neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the celebration of diuine Seruice, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments? And haue you a cheſt wherein to put the almes for the poore, with thrée lockes and keyes vnto it: and another Cheſt for the kéeping of the Bookes, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb facs="tcp:84:4"/>
Veſſels, and Ornaments of the Church? Or where are they kept ordinarily?</p>
               <p n="5">5 In the ſaid Cheſt, haue you a Regiſter booke in Parchment, wherein to regiſter the Chriſtenings, Weddings, and Burials? And is the ſame booke written and kept in all points according to the Canon? And is the Chriſtian name of the mother as well as of the father, therein duly regiſtred? And is there a tranſcript thereof tran<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitted euery yéere into the Biſhops principall Regiſtry? Haue you alſo a faire Paxer-booke, wherein euery Preacher which is a ſtranger, is to ſubſcribe his name, the day when he preached, and by whoſe authority he is licenſed? And haue you alſo a Table ſet vp in your Church, of the degrées, wherein by Law men are prohibited to marrie?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Is your Church or Chappell, with the Chancell thereof, as alſo the Veſtrey, and the Church Porch (if you haue any) and your Parſonage houſe or Vtcarage-houſe, and all other houſes thereto belonging, your Pariſh Almes-houſe and Church-houſe, in good reparations? And are they imployed to godly and their right holy vſes? And if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them be ruinated and waſted, in whom is the default? And is your Church, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and Chappell, decently and comely kept, as well within as without? and are the ſeats in them well maintained, and the bottomes of them either boarded or paued? the Stéeple and Bels preſerued, the windowes in no part ſtopt vp, but well glazed, the roofe and wals cleane, the whole floore kept paued, plaine and euen, and all things there in orderly and decent ſort, without duſt rubbiſh, ſtraw or litter, or any thing that may he either noyſome or vnſéemly for the houſe of God? The Pariſhioners vſing none but Peſſes and faſt matts in their ſeats, as néed ſhall require?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Are there any armes and furniture for ſouldiers, or other munition, ladders, buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, timber, or any other implements for publike or priuate vſe, ſtored and kept in your Church, Veſtry, Sléeple, or any other part of the Church-buildings? How long hath it been ſo? And by whoſe authority or direction?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Is there any in your Pariſh, that hath or doth refuſe to contribute towards the reparation of your Church, or towards the prouiſion of ſuch things as belong there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Is your Church-yard or Chappell-yard encloſed and well fenced, and kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abuſe? and if not, whoſe is the default? Hath any perſon within your memory, or that you haue credibly heard of, incroached vpon the Church-yard, by ſetting vp any kind of building or fence vpon it, or by opening any doore, gate or ſtile into it? Hath any vſed that place (conſecrated to an holy vſe) prophanely or wickedly? Hath any vſed any chiding, brawling or quarrelling words, or ſtrucken any perſon either in the Church or Church-yard? Hath any perſon behaued himſelfe rudely and diſorderly in either; or vſed any filthy or prophane talke, or any other rude and immodeſt behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in them? Is there any ordinary paſſage vſed through the Church, or any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon walking therein, or carrying of burdens, or playing of children? Or haue any other Playes, Feaſts, Banquets, Suppers, Church-ales, Drinkings, Temporall Courts, Léets, or Lay-iuries, Muſters, exerciſe of dancing, ſtoole-ball, foot-ball, or the like, or any Faires, or Markets, boothes, ſtalls or ſtandings; or any other prophane vſage béene ſuffered to be kept in your Church, Chappell, or Church-yard? Haue any annoyed your Church-yard or the fences thereof, by putting in of cattell, by hanging vp of cloathes, or by laying any duſt; dung, or any other filthineſſe there? or by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king water therein, eſpecially againſt the Church-wals? When graues are digged, are they made ſix-foot déepe (at the leaſt) and Eaſt and Weſt, and are the bones of the dead piouſly vſed, and decently interred againe, or laid vp in ſome fit place, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemeth Chriſtians? And is the whole conſecrate ground kept frée from ſwine and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther naſtineſſe?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Doth your Clarke or Sexion, or any Conſtable or Bailiffe, or any other perſon (by occaſion or pretence of any ſecular office or ſeruice whatſoeuer) at any time take
<pb facs="tcp:84:4"/>
vpon him, within the Church or Church-yard, to proclaime any Seſſions, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appearance, or to warne any Courts or other méetings, or buſineſſe? or to cry any hawkes, dogs, or other cattell, or any thing elſe: or to publiſh any Precepts, or other writings or Orders, for any Lay-occaſion, or buſineſſe whatſoeuer? for ſuch things ſhould rather be done in the market, or without at the Church-yard ſtile, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by ſupreme authority it be otherwiſe commanded.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Are your Church-wardens carefull to take ſpeciall order, that no dogs be at any time ſuffred to come into the Church, to the diſturbance of the diu'ne Seruice, and the polluting of that holy place of the Chriſtian congregation? And do any of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants (of what condition ſoeuer) or of their company, bring their hawkes into the Church, or vſually ſuffer their dogs of any kind to come with them thither, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the houſe of God, and his holy worſhip, and to the great ſcandall of the Chriſtian profeſſion?</p>
               <p n="12">12 What Legacies haue béen giuen to the vſe and benefit of your Church, and how haue they béene beſtowed? who hath receiued and detained them without due imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Doth any detaine or imbozell, or hath ſold and made away any of the Church goods, or vſed or imployed them otherwiſe, than by Law they ought to do? Haue you any Stocke or yéerely Reuenew belonging to the Church? what is it? how is it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Is your Church full, or vacant of an Incumbent? And if vacant, who receiueth the fruits thereof, and who ſerueth the Cure, and by what authority? And is it a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, or Vicarage, and Preſentatiue, or Donatiue? Or haue you but a ſtipendar<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Prieſt only? what is the common value &amp; means of his place known or reputed to be?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Is there in your Pariſh, or any where about you (that you know or haue heard of) any Church, Chappell, or Oratory, now demoliſhed, or likely to be ruined, or that is conuerted to any priuate or ſecular vſe?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Hath any priuate man, or men, of his or their owne authority (for ought you know) erected any pewes, or builded any new ſeates in y<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Church or Chancell? And what pewes or ſeats haue béene of late yeares new built, by whoſe procurement, and by whoſe authority? And are all the pewes and ſeates vniforme therein, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that they which are in them may all conueniently knéele downe together in the time of prayer, and haue their faces vp Eaſt-ward, toward the holy Table? And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that men and women do not fit promiſcuouſly together? Is the middle alley of the Church, or any of the other alleyes or Iles, or the body of the Chancell, built vpon (in any part thereof) for the ſetting vp of pewes or ſeats; or for the inlarging of anythere adioyning? Are there alſo any kind of ſeats at the Eaſt and of the Chancell, aboue the Communion Table, or on either ſide vp euen with it? And is the Chancell fully diuided from the body of the Church, and how, or in what manner?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Are there any priuy cloſets, or cloſe pewes in your Church? Are any pewes ſo loſtily made, that they do any way hinder the proſpect of the Church or Chancell, or that they which are in them be hidden from the face of the congregation? What gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries alſo or ſcaffolds haue you in your Church? How are they placed, and in what part of the Church? When were they built, and by what authority? Is not the Church large enough without them to receiue all your owne Pariſhioners? Is any part of the Church hidden or darkened thereby, or any of the Pariſhioners annoyed or offended by them?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Are any Tombes or Monuments for the dead, ſuffered to be erected, without the good licence and approbation of the Ordinary firſt ſhewed to the Church-wardens? Are there any ſo made, that they cumber ſome roome which may not well be ſpared; or trouble any ſeat or paſſage; or hinder the proſpect of the Church or Chancell, or the light of any window; or be inconuenient to the Miniſter in executing any part of the
<pb facs="tcp:84:5"/>
diuine Offices; or be ſo ſet vp, as to giue any ſcruple or offence to mens Chriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions in their holy prayers and adoration? Are any other meane toyes and childiſh gew-gawes (ſuch as the fonder ſort of people prepare at ſome burials) ſuffered to be faſtened vp in your Church at any ones pleaſure? or any Garlands and other ordinary funerall Enſignes to hang, where they hinder the proſpect, or vntill they grow foule and duſty, withered and rotten? And is your Church-yard peſtered and cloyed with frames of wood, piles of brick, or ſtones laid ouer the graues? Do any take vpon them (as they pleaſe) to ſet vp or lay great ſtones there at the head and foot of any graue, without the Incumbents leaue and the licence of the Ordinarie?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Hath any in your Pariſh defaced, or cauſed to be defaced, or purloyned any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents or Ornaments in your Church, or any Inſcriptions of Braſſe, any Lead, or Stones there, or any part of the Glaſſe-windowes, or the Organs? When was it done, and by whom?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Hath any Popiſh Recuſant, being lawfully excommunicate, or any other excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated perſon béen buried in your Church or Church-yard, before abſolution from that cenſure and excommunication obtained? And if yea, then by whom, and when?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Be the profits, tithes, or any commodities Eccleſiaſticall, belonging to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage or Vicarage of your Pariſh, conuerted to the vſe and benefit of the Patrons, or of any other but the Incumbent, and by them receiued and detained? And how long haue they béene ſo? And is there but a Curate or ſlipendary Prieſt kept in any place, where you haue heard, or do belieue an Incumbent ſhould be poſſeſſed, and what allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hath be?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Is there any other Cure annexed to your Pariſh, or any Chappell of eaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſame? How are they ſerued, by whom, and vpon what allowance? Is there any other kind of Chappell or Chappels within the precincts of your Pariſh? To whom do they belong? When were they erected? and when conſecrated? Haue you in your Pariſh any houſe or houſes, whereof any roome is ordinarily vſed for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſaying the diuine Seruice, and adminiſtring the holy Communion? How long hath it béene ſo? and by what authority or licence?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Haue you a true Terrier of all the Glebe-lands, Meadowes, Gardens, Orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Houſes, Stockes, Implements, Tenements, and portions of Tithes, within your Pariſh, or without, belonging to your Parſonage or Vicarage, taken by the view of honeſt men in your ſaid Pariſh, appointed by the Ordinary? And is it ſafely kept and preſerued, and in whoſe hands? And hath there a true copie thereof, vnder the hands of the Miniſter and Church-wardens, béene tranſmitted and laid vp in the Biſhops Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry, there to continue for a perpetuall memory thereof? And if you haue no ſuch Terrier yet made, you the Church-wardens and Side-men, together with your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Vicar, or in his abſence, your Curate, are now appointed to make diligent inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the premiſes, and to make, ſubſcribe, and ſigne the ſaid Terrier, and to bring in a true copie of it into the Biſhops Regiſtry, within thrée moneths after the receit of this booke of Articles?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Concerning the Miniſters, Preachers, and Lecturers.</head>
               <p>IS your Miniſter, Parſon, Vicar, or Curate reputed to be a Graduate in either of the Vniuerſities, yea, or no? And if he be a Graduate, then of what degrée is he? what is his Chriſtian and Sire-name?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Is your Miniſter a licenſed Preacher, yea or no? And if he be licenſed, then by whom? Doth he preach vſually in his owne Cure, or in ſome other Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell neare adioyning, where there is no Preacher, once euery Sunday? And how often
<pb facs="tcp:84:5"/>
hath he béene negligent in ſo doing? Doth he alſo preach ſtanding, and in his C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and Gowne (not in a Cloak) with his Surplice and Hood alſo if he be a Graduate, and with his head vncouered? And if hee be not a licenced Preacher, doth he take vpon him in his owne Cure, or elſewhere, to expound any Scripture, or matter of doctrine, or doth he kéepe himſelfe only to the reading of Homilies publiſhed by authority; and beſides, procure Sermons to bee preached amongſt you, once euery moneth at leaſt, by ſuch as are lawfully licenced? And doth hee or his Curate vpon euery Sunday when there is no Sermon, read ſome one of the Homilies preſcribed by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and before the ſaid Homily, vſe that forme of exhorting to prayer (onely) which is preſcribed in the fifty fifth Canon, and no other prayer of his owne, either before or after it?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Is your Miniſter reſident with you vpon his benefice? or if abſent, how long time hath he béene ſo? and where is he reſident for the moſt part? And doth he in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence make allowance to the poore, and what allowance doth he make? Hath he any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Benefice, and doth he ſupply his abſence by a Curate ſetled and dwelling in your Pariſh, that is licenced to preach, and what allowance doth he make to his Curate, and how often in the yéere comes he thither himſelfe?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Is your Curate licenced by the Biſhop of the Dioces? And doth your Miniſter or Curate ſerue any more Cures then one? If yea, then what other Cure doth he ſerue, and how farre are his Cures diſtant one from the other?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hath any being no Prieſt, or Deacon, preſumed at any time (under pretence of being a graduate, or a Scholler of the Vniuerſity) to read common prayers openly in your Church or Chappell; or to ſerue the Cure of your Pariſh, or to preach there; Hath any Deacon not hauing receiued the full order of Prieſthood, taken vpon him alone to adminiſter the Communion in your Church or Chappell; You are to preſent the names of any, that haue herein offended as farre as you know or belieue?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Doth your Miniſter, Preacher, or Lecturer, onely read the Communion Seruice, commonly called the ſecond Seruice, at the Communion Table? Doth he begin his Sermon at any time, or part of the diuine Seruice, but immediately after the Beliefe called the Nicéene-créed? Doth hee before his Sermon vſe any forme of Prayer which is of his priuate conceiuing or collecting, and of his owne inuenting or chooſing. or doth he containe himſelfe within that briefe forme onely, which is preſcribed by the Church (in the 55. Canon) thereby only to exhort and moue the people to ioyne with him in Prayer for Chriſts holy Catholike Church, and for the Kings moſt excellent Maieſty (naming him and his royall Titles) for the Quéene, the Prince, and the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Iſſue; for the Arch-biſhops alſo and the Biſhops; for the Councell, the Nobility, the Magiſtracy, and commons of the land, and to giue thanks to God for the faithfull departed out of this life? And then (this mouing to prayer being done, as briefly as conuenientlly may be) both he alwayes conclude it with the Lords Prayer?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doth your Preacher or Miniſter at the cloſe of his Sermon, wholly forbeare to vſe any kind or forme of Prayer (not being preſcribed,) as alſo to pronounce the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (out of the Pulpet) wherewith the Church uſeth to diſmiſſe the people? But doth he there conclude only with, Glory to God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt: and then comming from the Pulpit (if the Sermon were made within the Church or Chappell) doth he, or whoſoeuer then officiates, at the ſame place where he left before the Sermon, proceed to reade the remainder of the divine Seruice; and at the cloſe of all to give the Bleſſing, and not before?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Doth euery Prieſt and Deacon in your Pariſh daily ſay the Morning and Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer, either priuately or openly, vnleſſe <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bée vpon lawfull cauſe hindered?
<pb facs="tcp:84:6"/>
Doth your Curate ſay the ſame daily in your Church or Chappell, with the tolling of a Bell before hée begin? Eſpecially doth your Miniſter or Curate do it on euery Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and Holiday, and their Eues, and on the day of the conuerſion of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Saint <hi>Barnabies</hi> day, and euery day of the holy Wéek next before Eaſter; as alſo on all Wedneſdaies and Fridayes, at fit and vſuall times, according to the forme preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the Booke of Common Prayer, in a reuerent manner ouer, and as audibly and diſtinctly as he vſeth to Preach? Doth he alſo read all thoſe Pſalmes and Leſſons, and no other, with the Collect, Epiſtle, and Goſpell, which are appointed for the day? At the end of euery Pſalme, due they ſtand and ſay, Glory be to the Father, &amp;c. and doth hée leaue out and not read the Contents of the Chapters? After the Leſſons, doth he uſe no other Pſalme or Hymne, but thoſe which the Booke of Common Prayer hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed? Doth hée read the Créed of S. <hi>Athanaſſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (called the <hi>Quicunque vult,</hi>) on all thoſe dayes for which it is appointed, and the Commination on Aſh wedneſday, adding the Letany on euery Wedneſday and Friday?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Doth your Miniſter and Curate at all times, as well in Preaching or reading the Homilies, as in reading the Prayers and the Letany, in adminiſtring the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, ſolemnization of Mariage, burying of the dead, churching of women, and all other offices of the Church, duly obſerue the Orders and Rites preſcribed, without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, alteration, or addition of any thing? And doth he, in performing all and euery of theſe, weare the Surplice duly, and neuer omit the wearing of the ſame, nor of his Hood, if he be a Graduate?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Doth your Parſon or Vicar hauing a Curate vnder him, notwithſtanding read diuine Seruice himſelfe frequently and publikely at the vſuall times, both in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone and after noone, in the Church which hée poſſeſſeth? and doth hée alſo adminiſter both Sacraments, euery yéere in ſuch manner, and with the obſeruation of all ſuch Rites and Ceremonies, as are preſcribed in the Booke of Common Prayer in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe? and how oft in the yéere hath he done it?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Doth your Miniſter, Preacher, and Lecturer, euery yéere, of purpoſe and expreſly (yet not by way of diſputation, but by plain concluſion &amp; determination) only teach and declare the lawfull authority which the King hath ouer the State, both Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuill; and the iuſt aboliſhing of all Popery and forraigne power or iuriſdiction o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſame?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Hath your Miniſter, or any Preacher among you publiſhed in his Sermons any doctrine, which is new and ſtrange, and diſagréeing from the Word of God, and from the Articles of Chriſtian Faith and Religion, agréed on and publiſhed <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1562. Or hath he taught any thing, which he would haue the people religiouſly obſerue and belieue, but that which is agréeable to the Scriptures, and that which the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Fathers and ancient Biſhops haue gathered out of that doctrine, according to the Canon, as you conceiued, or haue béene informed by others of better iudgement?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Doth your Miniſter goe to the adminiſtration of holy Baptiſme, euer immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the ſecond Leſſon? Doth he alwayes (at firſt) aske, whether the child bée baptized or no? Afterward doth he euer vſe and neuer omit, both to take the child in his hands, and alſo to make the ſigne of the Croſſe, to as to touch the childs forehead in making the ſame? Doth he at any time publikely baptize but in the Font, or with any Baſon, Bucket, or Paile, or other veſſell ſet into the Font? Hath he euer defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or willingly neglected, or refuſed to baptize any infant within the Pariſh, being in danger of death, notice thereof hauing béene giuen to him? And hath any child dyed without baptiſme, by his default?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Doth your Miniſter or Cur<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ten admoniſh the people, that they deferre not the baptiſme of their infants any <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ger, after they are borne than is preſcribed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:84:6"/>
vpon a great and reaſonable <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, declared withe Miniſter or Curate, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by him; nor that they procure them to bée baptized at home without great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Hath your Miniſter admitted any perſon to anſwer as Godfather or Godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at the chriſtening of a child, that hath not before receiued the holy Communion, and is not able to recite the Lords Prayer, the ten Commandements, and the Articles of Beliefe, and to anſwer to the ſame, being required? And doth hée at the Font, as ſoone as he hath baptized any child, admoniſh them to bring the child to the Biſhop to be confirmed, as ſoone as it hath learned the Catechiſme?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Doth your Miniſter, euery Sunday and Holiday before euening prayer, halfe an houre or more, catechiſe and inſtruct the youth; and ignorant perſons of your Pariſh, both male and female in the ten Commandements, the Articles of Beliefe, and the Lords Prayer? And doth he vſe for that purpoſe, the Catechiſme ſet forth in the Book of Common Prayer, and diligently heare, inſtruct, and teach them in the ſaid Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme? Or what other Catechiſme doth he vſe either in publike or private: And be the youth and ignorant perſons of your Pariſh, ſent in due time vnto your Church, by them that ought to ſend them, to be catechized and inſtructed by the Miniſter? And if not, you are to preſent the names of thoſe that make default in ſending them, and of all thoſe that vſe not to come, or care not to learne.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Are your afternoone-ſermons (if there were wont to be any) turned into cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing by queſtion and anſwer, where and whenſoeuer there is no great cauſe appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the contrary? And is this truly and ſincerely performed, without mockery, or in ſhew only, and ſo, without any long or large diſcourſe (Sermon-wiſe) vpon the ſaid Queſtions and Anſwers? but only to explaine the ſame in few and briefe paſſages eaſie to be remembred?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Doth your Miniſter vſe to adminiſter the holy Communion, at leaſt thrice in the yéere (whereof once at Gaſter) to euery pariſhioner in your Pariſh, that is ſixtéene yéeres of age and upwards; and firſt to receive the ſame himſelfe, knéeling, on euery day that he adminiſtreth it to others; and to adminiſter it to none but to ſuch as doe knéele at the receiuing thereof? And doth he alwayes vſe the words of inſtitution, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Book of Common Prayer, without alteration, at euery time, that the Bread and Wine is renewed? Doth hée alſo vſe to deliuer the Bread and Wine to euery Communicant ſeuerally, and with his owne hand, repeating to euery one, all the words appointed to be ſaid at the diſtribution of the holy Body and blood of our Lord IESUS, and upon no pretence (till the Church appoint otherwiſe) omitting any part of the words, or ſaying them all but now and then to many at once? And is there warning giuen by him, to the Pariſhioners, publikely in the Church, at morning prayer the Sunday before euery time of his adminiſtring of the Holy Communion for their better preparation thereunto?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Hath your Miniſter admitted vnto the holy Communion any of his cure or flocke, which he openly known to liue in ſinne notorious, without Repentance, or any that haue maliciouſly and openly contended with their neighbours, before they bée reconciled; or any Church-wardens, or Side-m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n, who hauing taken their oathes to preſent to their Ordinary all ſuch publike offences, as they are particularly charged to enquire of in the Pariſh, have and doe notwithſtanding, wittingly and irreligiouſly incurre the horrible crime of periury, either in neglecting or refuſing to preſent ſuch publike offences, as they themſelues know, or haue heard to bée committed within your Pariſh?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Hath your Miniſter at any time admitted vnto the Communion any that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be preſent at publike prayers, or who are notorious deprauers of the Booke of Common Prayer, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, or of the Orders, Rites,
<pb facs="tcp:84:7"/>
or Ceremonies therein preſcribed; or of any thing contained in the thirty nine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, or in the Book of ordaining Prieſts and Biſhops? Or who haue ſpoken againſt or depraued his Maieſties Soueraigne Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, vnleſſe they and euery of them doe firſt acknowledge their repentance for their ſin, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to do ſo no more?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Doth your Miniſter or Curate admit any to the Communion, before they can ſay their Catechiſme, and be confirmed?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Doth your Miniſter together with the Church-wardens and Queſt-men, take diligent héed and care, not only that all and euery one of your owne Pariſhioners do receiue thrice euery yéere; but alſo, that no ſtrangers of any other Pariſh, doe come often and commonly to your Church, from their owne Pariſh Church, or do there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy Communion?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Doth your Miniſter, before the ſeuerall times of adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, admoniſh and exhort his Pariſhioners, if any of them haue their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence troubled and diſquieted, to reſort vnto him, or to ſome other learned Miniſter, and open their griefe, that they may receiue ſuch ghoſtly counſell and comfort, as their conſcience may be relieued, and by the Miniſter they may receiue the benefit of Abſolution, to the quiet of their Conſcience, and auoiding of all ſcruple? And if any man confeſſe his ſecret and hidden ſinnes, being ſicke or whole, to the Miniſter, for the vnburthening of his conſcience, and receiuing of ſpirituall conſolation or eaſe of minde from him, Doth he the ſaid Miniſter (or hath he at any time) by word, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or ſigne, openly or couertly, directly or indirectly, reueale and make knowne to any perſon whatſoeuer, any Crime or Offence, ſo committed to his truſt and ſecrecie?</p>
               <p n="24">24 Hath your Miniſter ſolemnized the Mariage of any perſon under the age of twenty one yéeres, without the conſent of their Parents or Gouernours; or hath hée maried any, which doe not audibly ſay and anſwer in all things appointed by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie; or any without a King, or in times prohibited, or without the Banes firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed thrée ſeuerall Sundaies or Holidaies, in time of diuine Seruice, in the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Churches or Chappels of their ſeuerall abodes, except they brought him a ſpeciall licence from the Arch-biſhop, or Biſhop of the Dioces, or his Chancellor ſo to doe? And both hée begin in the body of the Church, and then goe up to the Table, as to appointed? Alſo doth your Miniſter, ſo oft as there is any mariage, appoint to haue a Communion? After the Goſpell doth hee ſay a Sermon (if hée bée li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenced to preach) wherein to declare the office of man and wife, according to holy Scripture; Or elſe doth hee read that which the Church hath appointed to bée read at Matrimony?</p>
               <p n="25">25 Doth your Miniſter vſe the forme of thankſgiuing for women after childe-birth immediately before the Communion Seruice? Or hath hée admitted thereunto any women begotten with child in Adultery or Fornication, without licence of his Ordinary?</p>
               <p n="26">26 Doth your Miniſter carefully looke to the reliefe of the poore, and from time to time call vpon his Pariſhioners, to giue ſomewhat according to their abilities, to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and charitable vſes; eſpecially doth be enforce it vpon them with earneſt exhortation (as is preſcribed) at the time of the oblation or offering before the Communion, and vpon their ſick beds, or when they make their wils?</p>
               <p n="27">27 Doth your Miniſter or Curate reſort vnto ſuch as bée dangerouſly ſicke in your Pariſh (if he be ſent for, or notice of their ſickneſſe being given vnto him) to inſtruct or comfort them in their diſtreſſes, according to the order of the Book of Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, not omitting then eſpecially, to moue them earneſtly to liberality towards the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oore?</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <pb facs="tcp:84:7"/>28. If any being ſicke doe deſire the prayers of the Congregation, is it done at the time of diuine Seruice after the thrée Collects? and according to the forme in the Liturgie for the Viſitation of the ſick? and not onely by giuing their names to the Preacher, and mentioning of them in the Pulpit, before or after a Sermon?</p>
               <p n="29">29 Hath your Miniſter euer refuſed to bury any which ought to bee interred with Chriſtian buriall? Or hath hee deferred the ſame longer than hee ſhould? Doth hee goe before the Corps to the Graue, and there ſay the whole ſeruice appointed, not omitting the Leſſon or any other part? Doth be deuoutly kneele, when hee ſaith the prayers, and the Collects at buriall? or hath hee admitted any to Chriſtian buriall. which by the Lawes of the holy Church of this Realme, ought not to bee ſo interred?</p>
               <p n="30">30 Doth your Miniſter, being a Preacher, well ſtudied indiuinity, and hauing any Popiſh Recuſant or Recuſants in your Pariſh, labour diligently with them from time to time to reclame them from their errors? Or otherwiſe is he ouer conuerſant with them or ſuſpected to fauour them?</p>
               <p n="31">31 Hath your Miniſter, (or any other taking upon him the calling of a Miniſter) preached, baptized children (except in caſe of neceſſity) ſolemnized mariage, churched any women, or miniſtred the holy Communion in any private houſe or houſes? If yea, then where, when, and how often hath he done it?</p>
               <p n="32">32 Doe you know, or haue heard of any which are reputed to bee Miniſters (or of any other of the Laity, either Male or Female) that preſume to make matters of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity their ordinary Table-talk? Or that under pretence of holyneſſe and edification, take the liberty at their Trencher-meetings, or where ſeuerall company (not being all of the ſame family) are aſſembled, raſhly and prophanely to diſcourſe of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Or amidſt their cups, to diſpute or determine any Articles of Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or touching any point of doctrine or Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, at their owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, did to their owne phanſie? you ſhall name the perſons, times, and places, as far as you know or haue heard, and can remember.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Doth your Miniſter euery ſix moneths, in your Pariſh Church, openly in the time of diuine Seruice, vpon ſome Sunday, denounce and declare, excommunicate by name, ſuch as doe perſeuere in the ſentence of excommunication, not ſeeking to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued? And hath hee ſaid diuine Seruice, whiles any excommunicate perſon hath béene preſent in the Church? Or hath admitted any perſon, that hath beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, into the Church, without a Certificate of his abſolution from his Ordinary, vnder the ſeale of the office, and not by any note or Ticket only under the hand of the Regiſter, or any other Clerk? Or hath hee ſtayed or forborne to denounce any excommunication or ſuſpenſion or abſolution that hath béene ſent him from his Ordinary, further then the next Sunday or Holyday after receipt thereof under Seale?</p>
               <p n="34">34 Hath your Miniſter béene at any priuate méetings or conuenticies, to conſult there, about the impeachment or deprauing of the doctrine of the Church of England, or of the Book of Common Prayer, or of any part of the gouernment and diſcipline of the Church; or to practiſe any forme of their owne, either for worſhip or diſcipline?</p>
               <p n="35">35 Doth your Miniſter, vpon Sundayes at Morning Prayer, declare vnto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, what Faſting-dayes and Holy dayes are to bee kept, the wéek following?</p>
               <p n="36">36 Doth your Miniſter in the Rogation dayes, go the perambulation of the circuit of your Pariſh, ſaying and uſing the Prayers, Suffrages, and Thankſgiuing unto God, appointed by Law, according to his duty; thanking God for his bleſſings, and praying for his grace and fauour?</p>
               <p n="37">37 Doth your Parſon or Vicar maintaine and kéepe in due reparation, the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion-houſes,
<pb facs="tcp:84:8"/>
and all other edifices and fenſes belonging to his Parſonage or Vicarage without ſuffering them to grow into ruine or decay?</p>
               <p n="38">38 Hath your Miniſter taken upon him, to appoint, or to hold or continue any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or publike faſts, or méetings, for preaching or lecturing on any working-day, in his owne Pariſh or elſewhere, or propheſies or exerciſe, or any other ſuch thing, not being approued by his Ordinary for the time being?</p>
               <p n="39">39 Is your Miniſter ſtudious in holy Scripture, and abſtaineth from mechanicall trades, bodily labour, ſoliciting of cauſes in Law, common buying or ſelling of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or other Cattell and all other imployments not beſitting his calling and holy Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Doth he vſually weare a Gowne with a ſtanding coller, and ſléeues ſtrait at the hands, and a ſquare Cap? Doth he in iourneying vſe a cloak with ſléeues, commonly called a Prieſts-cloake, without guards, buttons, or cuts? Doth he at any time in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like weare any coife or wrought night-cap, but only a plaine cap of black ſilke, ſatten or veluet, and of a decent faſhion, and proper for Diuines? Doth he at any time goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in his dublet and hoſe without a Coat or Caſſock, or weare any light coloured ſtockings, long haire, deep bands, great ruffled booted, or any other vndecent thing? Or is hee any way exceſſiue in apparrell, either himſelfe or his wife?</p>
               <p n="40">40 Is your Miniſter ſuſpected, or knowne to haue obtained his Benefice by any Simoniacall compact, directly or indirectly? Or is he reputed to bée an incontinent perſon, a frequenter of Tauernes, Innes, or Ale-houſes, a common gameſter or play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at dice or cards, a common ſwearer or drunkard, a brabler or brawler, giuen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, vſury, brocage, or common merchandizing, or otherwiſe faulty in any other kind that is ſcandalous to his function?</p>
               <p n="41">41 Hath your Miniſter publikely in your Pariſh Church or Chappell, once euery yéere read ouer the Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſticall agréed upon by the Clergy of both Prouinces, <hi>An. Dom</hi> 1603, in ſuch manner as the ſame is commanded to be done?</p>
               <p n="42">42 Is there any in your Pariſh or reſorting thereunto, who hauing taken holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Prieſt or Deacon, doth uoluntarily relinquiſh and forſake his calling, and liues in the courſe of his life as a lay man? Or any that hauing béene ſilenced, or ſuſpended by authority, ſo remaineth without conforming himſelf in due obedience to the Church? And how doth he imploy his time; and where or whence hath he his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, as you know or haue heard?</p>
               <p n="43">43 Haue any béene admitted to preach in your Church, who doe not before the Church-wardens ſubſcribe their names in your booke prouided for that purpoſe, and the day when he or they preached, and the name of the Biſhop or Biſhops of whom they had licenſe to preach?</p>
               <p n="44">44 Hath any Preacher particularly impugned and confuted any doctrine deliuered by any other Preacher in the ſame Church, or in any Church néere adioyning, before he acquainted the Biſhop of the Dioces therewith, and receiued order from him, what to do in that caſe?</p>
               <p n="45">45 Haue you any Lecturer in your Pariſh, and on what day is your Lecture? If any ſuch be, doth he, twice at the leaſt euery yéere, read diuine Seruice both morning and euening, two ſeuerall Sundaies, publikely in his Surplice and Hood? And alſo twice in the yéere adminiſter both Sacraments, with ſuch Rites and Ceremonies as are preſcribed in the book of Common Prayer?</p>
               <p n="46">46 Doth the Lecturer (whoſoeuer he be) reade the diuine Seruice according to the Liturgie printed by authority, in his Surplice and Hood before euery Lecture?</p>
               <p n="47">47 Doth your Preacher or Lecturer behaue himſelfe in his Lectures and Sermons, as he ought to doe, teaching obedience, and edifying his auditory in matters of faith and good life, without intermedling with matters of State, or newes, or other diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:84:8"/>
not fit for the Pulpit; and alſo without fauouring or abetting Schiſmaticks or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts (that are at home, or are gone abroad) either by a ſpeciall prayer for them, or by any other approbation of them, and their ſchiſmaticall courſes?</p>
               <p n="48">48 Haue you any Lecture of Combination ſet vp in your Pariſh? And if ſo, is it read by a company of graue and orthodor Diuines, néere adioyning, and in the ſame Dioces? And doth euery one of them Preach in a Gown, and not in a Cloake? And when and by whom were they appointed? And what be their names?</p>
               <p n="49">49 Is any ſingle Lecture (maintained by your Towne or otherwiſe) ſuffered to preach, he not firſt profeſſing his willingneſſe to take vpon him the cure of ſoules nor actually taking a Benefice or Cure, ſo ſoone as it may be fairely procured for him? What is his <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>at licence hath he? And hath he a ſetled contribution affixed to the Lecture <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is it arbitrary, and for this Lecturer onely? What ſumme doth it amount to ordinarilly? By whom is it uſually paid or collected or of late yéeres hath béene?</p>
               <p n="50">50 If any Pſalmes be vſed to be ſung in your Church, before or after the morning and euening prayer, or before or after the Sermons (vpon which occaſions only, they are allowed to be ſung in Churches) is it done according to that graue manner (which firſt was in vſe) that ſuch doe ſing as can read the Pſalmes, or haue learned them by heart; and not after that vncouth and vndecent cuſtome of late taken vp, to haue every line firſt read, by one alone, and then ſung by the people?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. Concerning Matrimony.</head>
               <p>BE there any in your Pariſh, that haue maried within the degrées of affinity or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity, by the Law of God forbidden, as is expreſſed in a certaine Table publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by authority in <hi>Anno</hi> 1563. And if any haue ſo maried, what be their names, and where were they maried and by whom?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hath any béene maried ſecretly in private houſes, or without their Parents be Gouernours conſent ſignified, being under the age of twenty one yéeres?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Haue any perſons béene maried in your Pariſh, the Banes hauing not béene thrice publiſhed, thrée ſeuerall Sundayes or Holydayes in time of diuine Seruice? Who were the parties, and who were preſent at ſuch mariages; and what Miniſter maried them?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Haue any perſons by licence or without, béene maried in your pariſh Church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them at that time dwelling in your Towne? Or hath any mariage (that you know, or haue heard of) béene made at any time, by licence or without, but betwéene the houres of eight and twelue in the morning? Or was not the diuine Seruice then openly and duly ſaid, the Aſſembly being called together by the tolling or ringing of the Bels, as is at other times of diuine Seruice uſed? Or hath the Miniſter ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized any mariage (without Banes publiſhed) by vertue of any licence granted by the Arch-deacon or his Officiall, or by any other licence then of the Arch-biſhop or Biſhop of this Dioces or their Chancellors, or Vicars general, or the Commiſſary for faculties. And hath any Licence béene granted by any to ſuch perſons as were not of good ſtate and quality? Name the perſons and all particulars, as farre as you know or can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</p>
               <p n="5">5 What popiſh Recuſants, or their Children haue béene maried in your Pariſh? In what ſort was the matrimony ſolemnized? when? and by whom?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Do any perſon, being lawfully maried, liue aſunder? and in whom is the default, as far as you know or belieue?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doe any (heretofore diuorced, or not) kéep company at bed and board, with any
<pb facs="tcp:84:9"/>
other man or woman, then with the perſon that hée or ſhée were maried to? what be their names? when and where were they maried, and how long haue they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo together?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Haue you any in your Pariſh, which liue together as man and wife, and yet not known, by whom, where, or when they were maried?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Haue all new maried perſons (the ſame day of their mariage) duly receiued the holy Communion? If not, by whoſe default was it, as you conceive?</p>
               <p n="10">10 When any Mariage is ſolemnized in your Pariſh Church, is there any thing accuſtomed to bée ſaid or done (in the Church, or Chancell, at the Church doore, or in the Church-yard; either by the parties themſelues, or any other that accompany them, or that are then and there preſent) which is not preſcribed by the Rubricks of the Booke of Common Prayer, or the Canons of the Church, and which is impertinent or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely for that holy buſineſſe, and not befitting the reuerence of that ſacred place, in which they are aſſembled? ſpecifie what it is, and preſent the parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Concerning the Church-wardens and Side-men.</head>
               <p>BE the Church-wardens choſen by the Miniſter and Pariſhioners yéerely in Eaſter-wéek, according to the 89. Canon? And hath any taken vpon him to bée Church-warden, not being ſo choſen? Or hath any continued aboue one yeare in his office, without a new choice?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Haue any of the Churchwardens retained any of the Church-goods in their hands, and not made a iuſt account at the going out of their office, of what they haue receiued and ex<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ended; or not deliuered to their ſucceſſors, by Bill indented betwéene them, whatſoeuer money or other things belonging to the Church, that remained in their hands?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Are there in your Pariſh yéerely, two, thrée, or more diſcréet perſons, either choſen by the Miniſter and Pariſhioners in Eaſter-wéeke: or if they cannot agrée, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Ordinary to bée Side-men, or Aſſiſtants in ioynt office with the Church-wardens?</p>
               <p n="4">4 What rates or leuies (as you know or haue heard) are yéerely or commonly made in your Pariſh for Church vſes? What is the vſuall ſumme thereof ordinarily? and what are the particular vſes? or where are they written down, to which the ſame are for the moſt part imployed?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Do the Church-wardens and Side-men or Aſſiſtants, diligently ſée, that all the Pariſhioners do duly reſort to the Church, vpon all Sundaies and Holidayes, and there continue the whole time of diuine Seruice and Sermon; ſuffering no idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to walk, or talk, or ſtand idle, either in the Church, Church-yard, or Church, porch, during the time of diuine Seruice or Sermon; but cauſing them either to come into the Church, or elſe to depart? And haue they the ſaid Church-wardens and Side-men forborne, either for reward, fauour, or affection, to preſent them, that haue béene, or are negligent in comming to Church, or that vſe to walk or talk therein, or that haue bin found by them ſtanding idle, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> talking abroad, either in the Church-yard or ſtréets in the time of Diuine Seruice or Sermon, on Sundaies or Holydayes; or that haue not receiued the Communion yéerely, at the Feaſt of Eaſter, or within one moneth before or after?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Doe you know of any Church-wardens, which within forty dayes after Eaſter, in their yéere, did not exhibit to the Biſhop, or his Chancellor, the names and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of all the Pariſhioners, as well men as women, (which being of the age of 16. yéeres and upward) received not the Communion the Eaſter before? And haue
<pb facs="tcp:84:9"/>
you this laſt yéere exhibited a bill of them or are you <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſo ready ſo to doe?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Do the Church-wardens againſt euery Communion, adviſe with the Miniſter, about the prouiding of a ſufficient quantity of fine white-bread, and of good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome wine, for the number of Communicants that are to receiue? And is the wine brought in a cleane and ſwéet ſtanding pot of pewter or of other finer mettall? Vpon the Communion dayes doe your Church-wardens (immediately after the Sermon or Homily, and the Miniſters exhortation to remember the poore) gather the deuotion of the people in a faire and ſolemne manner, and put the ſame into the poore mans box?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Do the Church-wardens ſuffer any one to read divine Seruice in your Church at any time (whatſoeuer he pretend himſelfe to be) till ſufficient notice be taken, by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues or ſome other credible perſon) not only of his being in holy Orders, but alſo of his Licence to read there. Or do they ſuffer any man to preach, till hée haue ſubſcribed his name in their Paper book, and the day wherin he preached, and by whoſe authority he is licenced?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Hath the Church-wardens ſuffered the Church, Church-yard, or Chappell, to bée prophaned by Playes, Games, Feaſts, Banquets, Suppers, Church-ales, Drinkings, Temporall Courts, or Léets, Lay-iuries, Coroners inqueſts, Pariſh accounts, Muſters Wreſtlings, waſters, dancings, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, at any time acted, kept, or held in them?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Haue any man that you know or haue heard of, by ſpéech or writing, or vpon the aſſertion of any other man affirmed; that men ought not to take the office or the Oath of a Church-warden, or of preſenting at the Biſhops Viſitation? Or that the ſaid oath is unlawfully giuen them; or that being taken, it is but of courſe, and binds them not, nor néed to be regarded; or that (the ſaid oath notwithſtanding) it is free for them, neither to make inquiry, nor to anſwer; but to do what they liſt, and to leaue out and paſſe by whom they will, and what they will, in their Preſentments? Or do you know of any that haue abuſed the Church-wardens or other Sworn-men in your Pariſh, or giuen them euill words for executing of their office, or to diſhearten or deferr them from executing it as by hath and duly they are bound?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. Concerning the Pariſhioners.</head>
               <p>DO any in your Pariſh prophane any Sunday or Holyday, by any unlawful gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drinking, or tipling in Tauernes, Innes, Tobacco-ſhops, or Alehouſes, in the time of Common Prayer or Sermon; or by working, or doing the work of their trades and Occupations? Do any in your Pariſh buy or ſell, or kéep open their Shops, or ſet out any wares to be ſold on Sundayes or Holydayes by themſelues, their ſeruants, or apprentiſes; or haue they any other wayes prophaned the ſaid dayes? And hath the Kings Declaration concerning the lawfull ſports and recreations béene publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, yea or no. If ſo, when was it done, in what manner, and by whom?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Is the fifth day of November obſerued and kept in your Pariſh, with Prayer and Thankſgiuing unto God, in ſuch forme, as is by publike Authority appointed for the day? Is the 27. day of March alſo well and duely obſerued? are the Bels uſually rung in ioy of thoſe dayes? Do any in your pariſh take vpon them (in ſuch publike manner) to obſerue any other dayes in the yéere but theſe two?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Is there any in your Pariſh that hath béene heard to impugne or ſpeake againſt the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England, or the lawfull uſe of them; or to affirme by word or writing, that the forme of making and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, or any thing therin contained, is repugnant to the word of God or that the Government of this Church under his Maieſty by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſticall Officers is Antichriſtian? Or hath ſpoken reproachfully, or diſgracefully of the Kings Maieſties Courts Eccleſiaſticall, or of the procéedings thereof?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:84:10"/>4 Haue yon any in your Pariſh, that doe come to the Sermon only, and not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Service; or which uſe to come late to Church, and to depart from Church before the Bleſſing be given, wherewith they are to be diſmiſſed at the end of Seruice? Or that doe not reuerently behaue themſelues entring into the Church, and during the time of diuine Seruice? Do all (both men and women) deuoutly knéele, when the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall confeſſion of ſinnes, the Letany, the ten Commandements, and all Prayers and Collects are read, as well as Baptiſmes, Mariages and Burialls, as at other parts of the diuine Seruice? Do all vſe due and lowly reuerence, when the bleſſed name of the Lord IESUS is mentioned: and ſtand vp when the Articles of the Créed are read? Doe anymen couer their heads in the Church, (vnleſſe it be for infirmity, in which caſe they may only weare coifes or night-caps,) or then and there giue themſelues to bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, talking, or walking, and are not attentiue to the Prayers and Hymnes, and to heare Gods word read and preached? Doe all ſay Amen audibly, and make ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwers both in the Letany, and all other parts of diuine Seruice, as by the rule of the Common Prayer booke, are to bée made by the people?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Do any within your Pariſh, men or women, being ſixtéene yéeres of age and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or any other, lodging or commonly reſorting to any houſe in your Pariſh, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abſent themſelues, from your Pariſh Church or Chappell, vpon Sundaies and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydayes and other dayes appointed, at morning and euening Prayers, or refuſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Communion. or perſwade others from comming to Church, or receiuing the holy Communion?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Haue you any popiſh or puritanicall Recuſants in your Pariſh, that bée of inſolent behauiour, not without publike offence; or that do boldly b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe themſelues in perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeducing or withdrawing others, either abroad, or in their owne families from the Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of England? And how long haue the ſaid po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh or puritanicall Recuſants obſtinately abſtained, either from diuine Seruice, or from the Communion? Whether of any long time, or of late only?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Are there any in your Pariſh, who do abſent themſelves at any time from your owne Church, and do reſort to any other Pariſh or place to heare other Preachers? Or are there any in your Pariſh, that do communicate, or that doe baptize their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in any other Pariſh? Or doe the Pariſhioners of any other Pariſh reſort vnto your Church? how long haue they done ſo? and vpon what occaſion or licence?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Is there within your Pariſh or in any Pariſh néere you that you know of, in any houſe or family, any one that is called or reputed a Chaplaine, or that is known or ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to haue entred into holy orders? Or any that liue there in imployment as a Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler? Preſent there names if there bée any ſuch, and how long they haue béene there, and his name in whoſe houſe they kéepe.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Is there any in your Pariſh, who do refuſe to haue their children baptiſed, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to receive the Communion, at the hand of your Miniſter, becauſe he is no Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, or doth not edifie in their phanſie?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Doth any maried woman within your Pariſh, after child-birth neglect to come to Church according to the booke of Common Prayer to giue thanks to God for her ſafe deliuerance, valled in a decent manner, as hath béen anciently accuſtomed? doth ſhe alſo come to Church at or néere the beginning of diuine Seruice that day, and when the thankſgiuing for her is to bée ſaid, doth ſhe goe and knéele in ſome conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent place nigh to the Table, (but without the incloſure) while the Prieſt ſtanding within, by her, giueth thanks for her? And doth ſhe then offer her accuſtomed offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and receiue the holy Communion, if there be one?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Are there within your Pariſh or thereunto reſorting, any players on Stage, or with Puppits, or any Muſitians; Fidlers, Rimers, or Ieſters, which do vſe any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane or filthy paſſages, in their ſongs, ſpéeches, or geſtures, to the diſhonour of God,
<pb facs="tcp:84:10"/>
abuſe of Scripture, or the corrupting of good manners; or which doe publiſh any thing ſcandalous to the Church, or reproachfull to the holy Clergie?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Do you know of any man or woman, that hath abuſed their Parſon, Vicar, or, Curate, or any other that is in holy Orders, with contumelious words, or unciuill ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures or déeds, or behaued themſelues rudely towards them? Or that haue reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either the mariage or the ſingle life of Prieſts, or haue ſaid, or done any thing elſe that did redound to the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or diſhonour of their perſons or of their holy function and calling?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Haue you any in your pariſh that are commonly known, or reputed to bée blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers of Gods holy name, common and vſuall ſwearers, drunkards, vſurers, filthy ſpeakers, adulterers, fornicators, inceſtuous perſons, bawdes, concealers of fornicators or adulterers? Haue any in your pariſh béene detected of ſuch notorious crimes, and what penance haue they done for the ſame?</p>
               <p n="14">14 What corporall puniſhment for any ſuch, or any other offence, hath béen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted and changed into a pecuniary mulct or ſumme of money, by any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iudge exerciſing iuriſdiction within this Dioces, what was the ſumme of money by any of them ſo receiued and taken, and to what vſes was the ſame imployed? And vpon ſuch Commutations, was the vnfained repentance of the delinquent publiſhed in the Church? And hath Commutation béen granted to one and the ſame party aboue once, for any crime of the ſame kind</p>
               <p n="15">15 Do all Fathers, Mothers, Maſters, and Miſtreſſes, cauſe their children, ſeruants and apprentiſes to come to the publike catechizing on Sundayes and Holydayes, to be inſtructed and taught therein? And thoſe that do not their duties herein, in not ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to it, or not duly comming, or not learning and anſwering, you ſhall preſent their names?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Haue any in your Pariſh receiued or harboured any woman begotten with child out of wedlock, and ſuffered her to depart without puniſhment firſt inflicted on her by the Ordinarye You ſhall truly preſent as well the party harbouring, as harboured; and who is ſuſpected to be the father of the child?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Is any perſon or perſons ſuſpected or detected héertofore of incontinency, and therefore departing out of your pariſh for a ſeaſon, now returned againe? Or in what place elſe is he or ſhe now abiding to your knowledge, or as you haue heard? You ſhall not faile to preſent the whole truth in that behalfe, as far as you know?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Do all your pariſhioners, of what ſort ſoeuer, receiue the bleſſed Sacrament, thrice euery yéere at leaſt, and when they do receiue it, doe they all according as the Church expreſly them commandeth, draw néere, and with all Chriſtian humility and reverence come before the Lords Table? And not (after the moſt contemptuous and vnholy uſage of ſome, if men did rightly conſider) ſit ſtill in their ſeates or pewes, to haue the bleſſed Body and Blood of our Sauiour go up and down, to ſéeke them all the Church ouer?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Are there any deceaſed in your pariſh, whoſe laſt Wills and Teſtaments haue not yet béene proued? or did they dye inteſtate? And if ſo, who hath taken vpon him the adminiſtration of their goods, and whether by lawfull authority from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, or without? What be the names of ſuch deceaſed, and of their Executors and Adminiſtrators?</p>
               <p n="20">20 What perſons bée excommunicated in your pariſh, and for what cauſe to your knowledge? And how long haue they ſtood excommunicate? And do any of them, not being abſolued, preſume to be preſent in the Church at diuine Seruice? And do any familiarly uſe the company of ſuch as do obſturately ſtand excommunicate, knowing the ſame; and what be their names?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:84:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. Concerning Schoole-maſters, Phyſitians, Chirurgions, Midwives, Pariſh-clarks, and Sextons.</head>
               <p>HAue you any Schoole maſter in your Pariſh, that teacheth publikely or in any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſes? And if ſo, what is his name, and how long hath he béene there? Is there any teaching of Schollers to read or write in the Chancell, or in any part of the Church? Doth any Papiſt kéep a Schoole-maſter in his houſe, who commeth not to Church to heare diuine Seruice, and to receiue the holy Communion? What is his name, and how long hath he taught there or elſewhere? Doth your Schoole-maſter teach any Papiſts or Sectaries children, that come not to Church? Doth hée bring his ſchollers to Church, and duly inſtruct them all to learne the Catechiſme in the Book of Common Prayer, at the leaſt once euery wéeke; or what other Catechiſme doth hée teach? Is he of honeſt and ſincere life, and religion, and converſation? Is he a Gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and ſufficient to teach, and diligent in teaching and bringing up of youth?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Is any thing withholden or otherwiſe imployed, that hath béene giuen to the vſe of a ſchoole in your pariſh? What is it? by whom is it imbezelled?</p>
               <p n="3">3 What Phyſition or Chirurgion haue you in your pariſh, who not being a Doctor of Phyſick, or otherwiſe ſufficiently licenced in either of the Vniuerſities, doth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding practiſe phyſick? what other perſons haue you among you, either male or female, who take upon them to profeſſe or practiſe phyſick or chirurgery? And who be Midwiues in your pariſh?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Haue you a fit Pariſh-clark (aged 20. yéeres at leaſt) and a Sexton? Is your Clark or Sexton of honeſt life, able to read and write? Are his and the Sextons wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges duly paid without fraud or diminution, according to the ancient cuſtome of your pariſh? What are the ſaid wages by the yeare? By whom are the ſaid Clark or Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton choſen? Are both or either of them diligent in his office, and ſeruiceable to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter? Doth he kéepe the Church cleane and the doores locked? Is there any thing loſt or ſpoyled through his default?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Doth your Clark or Sexton take upon him to haue, or ſuffer any ſuperſtitious or any unſeaſonable ringing of the Bels at any time, or any ringing without good cauſe, ſuch as the Miniſter and Church-wardens haue not allowed? When notice is given of any Chriſtian paſſing out of this life, within the pariſh, doth he neglect to toll a paſſing-bell, or to ring preſently after the departure?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Doth your pariſh Clark or Sexton or any other of your pariſh exact or require more then the ordinary and accuſtomed Fée for any ſeruice done by him or them, in or <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at mariages chriſtenings and burials; or for any thing elſe concerning the ſame? or haue they refuſed to do their duties therein, untill they haue receiued what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. Concerning Eccleſiaſticall Officers.</head>
               <p>WHat peculiar or exempt Iuriſdictions know you of, within the compaſſe of this pariſh?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Are there any Eccleſiaſticall Officers exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Dioces, or any Miniſters or Clarks under them, who do take or exact any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary fées, for any cauſe that you know of, or by way of gratuity for expedition?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Haue any Church-wardens and Queſt-men, concealed and not preſented any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes or offences puniſhable in the Eccleſiaſticall Court? Or haue any ſuch offences, being by them preſented to the Chancellor, Arch-deacon, Officiall, or any other uſing
<pb facs="tcp:84:11"/>
Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction within this Dioces, béene ſuppreſſed or left unpuniſhed, for bribe, reward, pleaſure, friend-ſhip, feare, or any other partiall reſpect?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Are any aſſemblies called Veſtry-méetings, held in your Pariſh? when and how often are they? In what place, and by whom? Hath any thing (that you haue heard of) béene propoſed, treated or concluded therein, touching the diuine Seruice, or the doctrine and diſcipline of the Church? Or any thing medled with, for the gouerment of the Church or pariſh, which belongs to the Eccleſiaſticall cognition and Iuriſdiction?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Doth the Arch-deacon once in thrée yéeres, viſit and ſuruey your Church, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the repaires of the ſame, and vpon any defect found, hath he made certificate of it, as far as you know or haue heard?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Are there placed by the Regiſtrar, two Tables containing the ſeuerall rates and ſummes of all fées due to the Iudge, and other officers of your Courts; one in the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all place or Conſiſtory, where the Court is kept; the other in the Regeſtry; in ſuch ſort as euery man may come to vew the ſame without difficulty? and doth the Chancellor, Arch-deacon, or Officiall, or any other Miniſter of the Court, exact or extort any other greater fées or ſummes of money, then in the ſaid tables are contained?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doth the Arch-deacon his Officiall, or Surrogate, make commutation of any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; or doth the Chancellor, or any Surrogate under him commute or change any penance or corporall puniſhment, for any money, without the conſent of the Biſhop? And what money haue they or any of them receiued for ſuch commutation, and of whom? when, and what was the offence, for which any ſuch ſumme of money was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or appointed to be paid?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Doth the Chancellor, Arch-deacon, or Officiall, or any other perſon vſing Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall iuriſdiction, ſpéed any act in any cauſe, priuately of themſelues, and not in the preſence of ſome publike Notary or Actuary? Or (for want of them) in the preſence of two (or moe) ſufficient witneſſes, and then cauſe the ſame act to be regiſtred?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Is the number of Apparitors increaſed in this Dioces? And wherein, and in what manner is the Country ouerburthened or grieued by them? Hath any of them under pretence of authority, cited or ſummoned any perſon unlawfully; or hath any of them taken any reward for the concealing of any offence or ſin, or that the offenders might eſcape puniſhment? Who bée they that haue ſo done? Or do any of them take any fées that are not vſuall? Haue they threatned any to proſecute them, if they had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward giuen them? Or do any of them cauſe any party to appeare in any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Court within this Dioces, without a citation firſt obtained from the Iudge of the Court?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Hath any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge or Officer whatſoeuer, Aduocate, Regiſter, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, Clarke, or other ſuch Miniſters, any way abuſed themſelues in their Offices, contrary to the Lawes and Canons in that behalfe prouided, that you know of?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Doth the Regiſtrar or any of the Clarkes in Eccleſiaſticall Office, when any obtaine Abſolution from the Iudge, neglect to ſend forth the ſame under the Seale of the office, or doth any of them preſume to giue ſignification unto the Miniſter of the Pariſh, only by a Note or Ticket, under their hand, to the intent that notice therof ſhould be taken, or the ſame be publiſhed in the Pariſh by him?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Laſtly, haue you and every of you, by your ſelves read, or haue cauſed to be read to you, all theſe Article? Haue you well examined and inquired into euery particular therein intended? Haue you ſincerely, uprightly, and without any partial affection or concealement, preſented and made knowne all and euery of the offendors in any of the particulars, either as they are taken in truth to be, or by common fame reported?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:84:12"/>If you know of any other matter of Eccleſiaſticall cogniſance, worthy the preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in your iudgement and fit to be reformed by Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, though it be not expreſſed in theſe Articles, yet you ſhall likewiſe preſent the ſame by vertue of your oathes.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter alſo of every Pariſh may and ought to ioyne with the Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or other Sworn-men, for the preſenting of offences; and if they be ſo irreligious as not to do it, the Miniſter of himſelfe may and ought to preſent either the offences, or the Church-wardens and Queſt-men, for not preſenting, the ſame and is required in his Canonical obedience ſo to do.</p>
               <p>There muſt be diſtinct anſwer made to euery Article, and to euery branch thereof, as far as they know, or haue heard of any offence, otherwiſe the preſentment will not be admitted.</p>
               <p>And if (their Oath and all this punctuall direction and aduertiſement notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) any Church-wardens or other Sworn-men, ſhall follow the cuſtomary manner, and be careleſſe in inquiring and preſenting as they ought, then ſhall they not be able hereafter to ſay, that they had not faire warning to the contrary giuen them in the ſpirit of méekneſſe; or to complaine, that they are hardly dealt with, if (vpon informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and proofe otherwiſe had) they bée called to anſwer their wilfull periury, in ſome other Court, or courſe of iuſtice, for neglecting to inquire and preſent to all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars herein propoſed.</p>
               <p>And to the intent that all things aboue mentioned may (by the help of God) as well be kept, as ſet in good order, the Chancellor of the Dioces, and the Officiall, and all their Surrogates are hereby required, that ſo far as to them in their ſeuerall places it ſhall appertaine, they do faithfully inquire after all theſe things, and in all places of their Iuriſdictions exact a due obſervance of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:84:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Parſon, Vicar, or Curate of this Pariſh is required to receiue this book, and vpon the Sunday next after the receipt hereof, immediately after the Morning Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to publiſh the contents of the Proceſſe which is ſent forth. That all Preachers and Lecturers (if there be any in the Pariſh) together with the Church-wardens and two or thrée of the chiefeſt Pariſhioners beſide, as alſo all Phiſitians, Schole-maſters, Chirurgions, Midwiues, and Sequeſtrators and all other whom it doth concerne, may take notice of the day and place ſpecified in the ſaid Proceſſe, for appearance at the Lord Biſhops Viſitation: and after publication ſo made, this book of Articles is to be preſently delivered to the ſaid Church-wardens, for the vſe of themſelves and the reſt that are to make the preſentments.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ma. Elien</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
